<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article class="whitepaper" revision="1.0">
  <title>Advanced Techniques Tutorial for the RCT3 Custom Scenery
  Importer</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>11.12.2006</date>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>

        <date>11.12.2006</date>

        <author>
          <surname>Belgabor</surname>
        </author>

        <revdescription>
          <para>Initial version</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <author>
      <surname>Vodhin</surname>
    </author>

    <author>
      <surname>Belgabor</surname>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <tocchap>
    <tocentry></tocentry>
  </tocchap>

  <para>This tutorial will show you various advanced techniques using the RCT3
  Custom Scenery Importer.</para>

  <para>This document applies to the <application>RCT3 Importer</application>
  Version 16fix5.</para>

  <section>
    <sectioninfo>
      <date>11.12.2006</date>

      <author>
        <surname>Belgabor</surname>
      </author>
    </sectioninfo>

    <title>Creating simple advanced objects</title>

    <section>
      <title>Litter Bins</title>

      <para>Set <guilabel>Extra Parameters</guilabel> and <guilabel>Scenery
      Type</guilabel> to <guilabel>Litter Bin</guilabel> in the scenery
      settings. Set the <guilabel>Size Flag</guilabel> to <guilabel>Path Edge
      (Inner)</guilabel>. Maybe <guilabel>Path Edge (Outer)</guilabel> works
      as well.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Loudspeakers</title>

      <para>Set <guilabel>Extra Parameters</guilabel> to
      <guilabel>Loudspeaker</guilabel> in the scenery settings.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Passport Machines</title>

      <para>Set <guilabel>Extra Parameters</guilabel> to <guilabel>Passport
      Post</guilabel> in the scenery settings. Set the <guilabel>Size
      Flag</guilabel> to <guilabel>Path Edge (Inner)</guilabel> or
      <guilabel>Path Edge (Outer)</guilabel>.</para>

      <important>
        <para>Somebody please verify that setting the <guilabel>Size
        Flag</guilabel> is really necessary.</para>
      </important>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Photo Spots</title>

      <para>Set <guilabel>Extra Parameters</guilabel> to <guilabel>Vista
      Point</guilabel> and <guilabel>Scenery Type</guilabel> to
      <guilabel>Photo Point</guilabel> in the scenery settings. Set the
      <guilabel>Size Flag</guilabel> to <guilabel>Path Edge (Inner)</guilabel>
      or <guilabel>Path Edge (Outer)</guilabel>.</para>

      <important>
        <para>Somebody please verify that setting the <guilabel>Size
        Flag</guilabel> is really necessary.</para>
      </important>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Objects that conform to the terrain</title>

      <para>There are two modes of conformance.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Full conform</title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Scenery Type</guilabel> <emphasis>must</emphasis>
            be set to <guilabel>Flowers</guilabel>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>As <guilabel>Size Flag</guilabel> I only tested
            <guilabel>Full Tile</guilabel>, but <guilabel>1/4 Tile</guilabel>
            should also work. I have no idea how the latter actually works out
            if the object is bigger than the quarter tile though...</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set <guilabel>Flag</guilabel> 13 and
            <guilabel>Flag</guilabel> 14.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The model for the cover needs to be able to bend along both
            diagonals, so a simple plane out of two faces will not work. You
            need at least four faces with a vertex in the center of the model.
            Actually I didn't try that, my simplest model has 16 faces, a 2x2
            version of what I described.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Another disadvantage is that the engine is somewhat buggy
            with this, so sometimes you see the tile straight.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>This version does not work for terrain textured
            tiles.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Conform to one edge of the tile</title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Scenery Type</guilabel> probably doesn't matter
            here (I used <guilabel>Small Scenery</guilabel>).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Size Flag</guilabel> has to be
            <guilabel>Wall</guilabel> and the model has to be positioned
            accordingly.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set <guilabel>Flag</guilabel> 13 and
            <guilabel>Flag</guilabel> 14.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The object is then placed like a in-game wall and conforms
            to the edge this <quote>wall</quote> is placed at.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="s_textureovl">
    <title>Creating and using texture OVLs</title>

    <para id="help">This section is so far unwritten and needs your help. If
    you want to write it, please apply <ulink
    url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/e107_plugins/forum/forum_viewtopic.php?1129">here</ulink>
    or <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=549880">here</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="s_lights">
    <title>Creating working lights</title>

    <para id="help">This section is so far unwritten and needs your help. If
    you want to write it, please apply <ulink
    url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/e107_plugins/forum/forum_viewtopic.php?1129">here</ulink>
    or <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=549880">here</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="s_particleeffects">
    <title>Creating particle effect points</title>

    <para id="help">This section is so far unwritten and needs your help. If
    you want to write it, please apply <ulink
    url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/e107_plugins/forum/forum_viewtopic.php?1129">here</ulink>
    or <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=549880">here</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="s_fireworks">
    <title>Creating firework launchers</title>

    <para id="help">This section is so far unwritten and needs your help. If
    you want to write it, please apply <ulink
    url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/e107_plugins/forum/forum_viewtopic.php?1129">here</ulink>
    or <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=549880">here</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="s_benches">
    <title>Creating working benches</title>

    <para id="help">This section is so far unwritten and needs your help. If
    you want to write it, please apply <ulink
    url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/e107_plugins/forum/forum_viewtopic.php?1129">here</ulink>
    or <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=549880">here</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="s_bbss">
    <sectioninfo>
      <date>11.12.2006</date>

      <author>
        <surname>Belgabor</surname>
      </author>
    </sectioninfo>

    <title>Creating billboards and scrolling signs</title>

    <para>The creation of billboards and scrolling signs is very similar, so
    I'll discuss them simultaneously.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the model</title>

      <para>The only thing you need to keep in mind when you create a model
      for a billboard or scrolling sign is that the part that shows the user
      image (billboards) or scrolling text (scrolling sign) needs to be a
      separate mesh. It can be a single plane, but more complicated meshes are
      also possible (<abbrev>eg.</abbrev> the round scrolling sign that comes
      with the game).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>UV-Mapping</title>

      <para>That's where things get a bit tricky as RCT3 maps the
      image/scrolling text in a strange way.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Billboards</title>

        <para>You need to UV-map the mesh that will show the user image to the
        <emphasis>lower half</emphasis> of texture space
        <emphasis>upside-down</emphasis>. Do not overshoot.</para>

        <para>Here is a screen shot from Blender to show you how it's done
        (look at the coloured lines to get the orientation):</para>

        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="billboard.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Scrolling Signs</title>

        <para><emphasis>One full height</emphasis> of texture space is filled
        with the scrolling text, as billboards,
        <emphasis>upside-down</emphasis>. To prevent distortion you need to
        overshoot the mapping to the right, so it's width to height ration
        matches the mesh you apply it to.</para>

        <para>Here is a screen shot from Blender to show you how it's
        done:</para>

        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="scrollsign.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the OVLs</title>

      <para>Basically set everything up like for a normal scenery
      object.</para>

      <para>For billboards, select <guilabel>Billboard Texture</guilabel> as
      <guilabel>Texture Flags</guilabel> in the <guilabel>Mesh
      Settings</guilabel> window of the billboard mesh. You do not need to
      select a <guilabel>Texture</guilabel> or <guilabel>Texture
      Style</guilabel> for it.</para>

      <para>For scrolling signs, select <guilabel>Scrolling Sign</guilabel> as
      <guilabel>Texture Flags</guilabel> in the <guilabel>Mesh
      Settings</guilabel> window of the scrolling text mesh. In this case you
      need to select a <guilabel>Texture</guilabel>. It is shown in the
      preview when the user selects the sign in the menu. You can change the
      <guilabel>Texture Style</guilabel>, but other ones as the default
      <guilabel>SIOpaqueUnlit</guilabel> are untested.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Scenery Settings</title>

      <para>The best option is to load a billboard or scrolling sign SID from
      jonwil's collection <ulink url="http://www.sebar.com/jonwil">on his
      page</ulink>. You only need to set <guilabel>Extra Parameters</guilabel>
      to <guilabel>Sign</guilabel> for scrolling signs then.</para>

      <para>The basic setup for billboards is to set <guilabel>Flag</guilabel>
      26 and to keep <guilabel>Extra Parameters</guilabel> at
      <guilabel>None</guilabel>. You don't need to set
      <guilabel>Flag</guilabel> 26 for generic stalls with billboards.</para>

      <para>The basic setup for scrolling signs is not fully tested, but at
      least you have to set <guilabel>Extra Parameters</guilabel> to
      <guilabel>Sign</guilabel>. If that doesn't work, try to set
      <guilabel>Scenery Type</guilabel> to <guilabel>Sign</guilabel> and
      <guilabel>Size Flag</guilabel> to <guilabel>Path Center</guilabel> or
      <guilabel>Path Edge (Join)</guilabel>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="s_stallssas">
    <title>Creating stalls and special attractions</title>

    <para id="help">This section is so far unwritten and needs your help. If
    you want to write it, please apply <ulink
    url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/e107_plugins/forum/forum_viewtopic.php?1129">here</ulink>
    or <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=549880">here</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="s_lods">
    <sectioninfo>
      <date>23.11.2006</date>

      <author>
        <surname>Vodhin</surname>
      </author>
    </sectioninfo>

    <title>Working with Levels of Detail (LODs)</title>

    <para>We all want nice looking 3D models for RCT3 but we must remember
    that a lot of folks out there cannot use high detail models without
    lowering the performance of the game itself. It is now possible to use
    Level Of Detail (<acronym>LOD</acronym>) setting when importing your
    custom scenery into RCT3, a feature that will have thousands of RCT3 fans
    out there grateful for your hard work.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Definition</title>

      <para>First I'd like to explain a little about what
      <acronym>LOD</acronym>s actually do and how to plan your model.
      <acronym>LOD</acronym>s are simply a way of using multiple models for
      both different graphics settings and Draw Distances
      (<acronym>DD</acronym>). My computer's graphics card can handle some
      pretty complex 3D models, but other players' computers may not, so
      different <acronym>LOD</acronym>s become very helpful for making happy
      graphics cards.</para>

      <para><acronym>LOD</acronym>s also have assignable Draw Distances. You
      can set how far away a particular version of your scenery is displayed.
      If I'm over at one side of the park and I have a high detail model on
      the other, there really is no need for the computer to try to draw the
      whole thing off in the distance, or draw it at all if it's a tiny object
      that really doesn't need to be seen that far away. Remember that RCT3
      doesn't really know what your object is and it certainly can't decide to
      just drop certain faces in an attempt to reduce the detail levels (there
      are some rules it follows, but RCT3 still needs information to optimally
      work). You have to do that yourself- but don't worry! It's really
      easy!</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Considerations about the model</title>

      <para>First lets think about the scenery item itself. For this tutorial,
      I'm going to use a sign with only two levels of detail. You can have
      more if you like, and I think three or four is probably more than enough
      for more complex items. If you were making a simple wall, there probably
      should only be just one level of Detail, but if that wall had a window,
      you might want to make several detail levels if, say, you had a fancy
      window frame. Lets look at the first, High Detail model:</para>

      <para><inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="LODs02.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>

      <para>My sign is essentially a wall, with some extra pieces in the way
      of a frame and some decorations. Here I've made all the detail levels
      needed in one 3D file- I simply choose to import the meshes designed for
      the intended detail level. Note that I've named the meshes in my 3D file
      according to the detail level they represent: HD= High Detail level, LD=
      Low Detail level, and AD= Al Detail levels. For the High Detail version,
      I've chosen not to import the Low Detail Meshes and added HD to the end
      of the model name at the very top. Let's now look at the low detail
      version:</para>

      <para><inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="LODs03.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>

      <para>Here you'll notice that I've simply chosen to not import the High
      Detail meshes and only import the Low Detail ones. What you don't see in
      either of the two images above are the actual mesh settings- In my High
      Detail meshes I've used a Gloss Reflection for the lamps, something that
      isn't needed for the low detail version for two reasons: 1- the low
      detail version is either going to be seen from far away or 2- the
      player's computer isn't very powerful and will be displaying the Low
      detail version, so why bog the computer down further if you don't have
      to.</para>

      <note>
        <para>I've also included a DS in the Mesh Names that I intend to use a
        double sided texture setting- very helpfull for my worn out little
        brain.</para>
      </note>

      <para>You will also notice that the name for this model in the top of
      the form has LD added to the end, to help identify it as a Low Detail
      model in the main <guilabel>Create OVL</guilabel> window. Again,
      remember that there is only one 3D model, I'm only changing what meshes
      to import for different detail levels. The model name at the top is used
      only by the importer and can be anything you want.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setting up the LODs</title>

      <para>Lets now look at the two Detail Levels now set up and give them
      their Draw Distances:</para>

      <para><inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="LODs01.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Models</guilabel> list (top) shows the two unique
      Detail Levels of the model I'm using. Note that this piece of scenery
      has some Effect Points and I've only set them up on the High Detail
      version. This is because Effect Points affect the entire Scenery OVL,
      not the individual Detail Level versions. If you add a light Effect
      Point to the high detail version, it will appear for all other versions
      of this piece.</para>

      <para>The bottom window is where you assign the Draw Distances for each
      Level Of Detail version you have made. The numerical values are in the
      same Modeler Units that you may already be familiar with: a value of 4
      would be the same as one RCT3 grid Square. So, in my examples here my
      High Detail version will be visible from 8 RCT3 grid squares away and
      the Low Detail version will be visible from 96 RCT3 grid squares
      away.</para>

      <para>What does that actually mean? Remember that you are making
      versions of your scenery piece at different Detail Levels to be shown
      based on what the player's Detail Level Settings (in their graphics
      settings menu) are set at. So what's going on with this Draw Distance
      setting?</para>

      <para>Well, each Detail level will be visible up to that distance away
      from the player's current position in the game: If their Detail levels
      are set low, then the Low version will draw from anywhere between 0 and
      (in my example) 96 RCT3 grid squares away.</para>

      <para>If the player has higher Detail Levels set, then the High detail
      model will be visible anywhere from 0 to 8 RCT3 grid squares away, and
      then the Low Detail version will then replace it from that point up to
      96 RCT3 grid squares away.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New Observation</title>

      <para>The Draw Distance value entered, while it does affect how far away
      the model will be visible, it also decides where the detail level is on
      the Detail Level Slider in the Graphics Settings LOD menu. I just made a
      piece with 5 levels of detail, set at (High) 32, (Medium) 64, (Low) 128,
      Extra-Low) 192, and (Ultra-Low) 384. These values caused the detail
      levels to change only at one extreme end of the scale: in order to view
      the lower detail levels I had to slide the control all the way over to
      the left, until it wans nearly off.</para>

      <para>The values entered here might just be a subtraction from a fixed
      value- if you labeled the scale 4000 on the Left to 0 on the Right
      (values found in the <application>Importer</application>) then my model
      changes at intervals equal to these Draw Distance Values entered above
      on that scale.</para>

      <para>The last thing I want to point out is where the player's actual
      Point Of View originates from: If you start the Attract Sequence Editor
      (<keycombo>
          <keycap function="control">Ctrl</keycap>

          <keycap function="shift">Shift</keycap>

          <keycap>0</keycap>
        </keycombo>) and place a camera (insert) and then back away, you will
      notice that the camera is about 1.5 RCT3 grid squares behind where you
      think you actually were. This offset needs to be considered into your
      Draw Distance settings: I always add a value of 8 to my intended Draw
      Distance, which adds 2 RCT3 grid squares to the viewing distance. Just
      something to remember.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Final Words</title>

      <para>Finally, in closing. So what distances should you use? Well, that
      depends on the size and type of the object. RCT3 will impose different
      Draw Distances based on what the player has set in their Graphics
      Settings, not just the Detail Levels. There are different Detail and
      Draw Distance settings for different types of scenery, too: A tree can
      have a whole different set of levels than the path items, which in turn
      could have different levels than rides, supports, shops,
      etcetera.</para>

      <para>Think about your object, how big or important it is when viewed
      from various distances, and then consider that the player's screen is
      only truly 2D in nature, and at some point any extra features that make
      your object 3D just cannot be drawn because there are only so many
      pixels the computer can actually use. A good example to look for are the
      heads of the peeps: at some point you will be too far away for the
      peep's ears to be drawn. If you were making a peep model, then you would
      make a detail level that does have some kind of simple ears (remember
      that Low Detail Levels are used on some computers when up close), but
      how complicated do they need to actually be?</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="s_alphatextures">
    <title>Working with transparent textures</title>

    <para id="help">This section is so far unwritten and needs your help. If
    you want to write it, please apply <ulink
    url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/e107_plugins/forum/forum_viewtopic.php?1129">here</ulink>
    or <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=549880">here</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="s_recoltextures">
    <title>Creating and using recolorable textures</title>

    <para id="help">This section is so far unwritten and needs your help. If
    you want to write it, please apply <ulink
    url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/e107_plugins/forum/forum_viewtopic.php?1129">here</ulink>
    or <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=549880">here</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="s_animtextures">
    <title>Creating and using animated textures</title>

    <para id="help">This section is so far unwritten and needs your help. If
    you want to write it, please apply <ulink
    url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/e107_plugins/forum/forum_viewtopic.php?1129">here</ulink>
    or <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=549880">here</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="s_texturestyles">
    <title>Extensive discussion of texture styles</title>

    <para id="help">This section is so far unwritten and needs your help. If
    you want to write it, please apply <ulink
    url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/e107_plugins/forum/forum_viewtopic.php?1129">here</ulink>
    or <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=549880">here</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Some information can be found on <ulink
    url="http://belgabor.vodhin.net/facts">Belgabor's facts &amp; figures
    page</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Credits</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The docbook css used for the html version of this document is
        based upon the one created by <ulink
        url="http://www.karakas-online.de">Chris Karakas</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>This CSS stylesheet uses <ulink
        url="http://www.matterform.com/qbullets/index.php">QBullets</ulink> in
        links. Thanks to Matterform Media for providing QBullets for free. If
        you plan to use them on your website, please observe the <ulink
        url="http://www.matterform.com/qbullets/usage.html">QBullets usage
        terms</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para role="matterform"><ulink
    url="http://www.matterform.com/"><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="/images/qb_credit.gif" scale="100" scalefit="0" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></ulink></para>

    <para><ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/"><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="http://sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=181524&amp;type=4" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="pdf">
          <imagedata fileref="/images/sflogo.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="chm">
          <imagedata fileref="/images/sflogo.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></ulink></para>
  </section>
</article>