<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Installing Custom Scenery</title>

  <para>Installing Custom Scenery is not a difficult task. There are a few
  things to consider though, like what file extension the pack might be in
  among other things. Here is a walkthrough for those who need help.</para>

  <important>
    <para>In the following tutorial <filename>&lt;RCT3 dir&gt;</filename> will
    be used as a placeholder for the directory you installed RCT3 to. Most
    commonly this is</para>

    <para><filename>C:\Program&nbsp;Files\Atari\RollerCoaster®&nbsp;Tycoon&nbsp;3</filename></para>

    <para>but that may differ on international versions or maybe
    <application>RCT3 Gold!</application> or <application>RCT3
    Platinum!</application> (or when you installed it to a custom directory).
    One thing you might easily miss is that some verisons leave out the
    trademark sign and it looks like this:</para>

    <para><filename>C:\Program&nbsp;Files\Atari\RollerCoaster&nbsp;Tycoon&nbsp;3</filename>
    </para>
  </important>

  <section>
    <title>Downloading Custom Scenery</title>

    <para>The first thing needed to know is how to get Custom Scenery, or
    <acronym>CS</acronym> for short.</para>

    <para>The largest way to get these sets is to download them from a
    third-party uploader, such as Rapidshare or Megaupload. Both options have
    free downloading capability and good sets can remain in storage
    indefinitely.</para>

    <para>Another option is to download from private servers hosted by many
    people from around the world. Both Vodhin and errt have great sites to
    download from and have a large selection of objects. One thing to keep in
    mind though, is that many of these servers require registration before you
    download any objects.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Unpacking Custom Scenery</title>

    <para>Once you have downloaded the set, you need to unpack it.</para>

    <para>There are three main formats that <acronym>CS</acronym> sets are
    downloaded in. The most common is in the <filename>.zip</filename> format
    and can be unzipped by most computers without having to download any extra
    software. The next most common is the <filename>.rar</filename> format,
    which requires 3rd party software to unpack. Only a few sets, such as
    MaxInfinity’s Gothic Wall set, are packaged as <filename>.rar</filename>
    files.</para>

    <para>The third format is in the form of a downloaded executable file. Not
    too many sets are downloaded in this manner; there are too many unknowns
    to make this an efficient method.</para>

    <para>Occasionally, you might find a set that is an executable packaged as
    a <filename>.zip</filename> for memory reasons. Just unzip it, and run the
    executable.</para>

    <para>The best place to unpack your downloaded <acronym>CS</acronym> sets
    is to set aside a folder on the desktop to download them to. You can have
    folders within that folder that contain unopened sets and keep the
    original downloads if the set becomes corrupt for some reason.</para>

    <para>Do <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> unpack or download your
    <acronym>CS</acronym> sets into the
    <filename>&lt;RCT3&nbsp;dir&gt;\Style\Themed</filename> folder as this is
    the leading cause of errors.</para>

    <para>After the <acronym>CS</acronym> set is unpackaged in a designated
    spot, open the folder with the set’s name. You should see two or more
    <filename>.ovl</filename> files and a few folders, the number depending on
    the number of objects in the set. If you only see a folder with the name
    of the set on it, then copy that folder into your storage spot (if
    necessary renaming the <emphasis>OUTER</emphasis> folder
    <emphasis>ONLY</emphasis>).</para>

    <para>Check to see if the required files are in there.</para>

    <para>After this point, check to see if a ReadMe folder was downloaded. If
    so, <emphasis>READ IT!</emphasis> There are a few sets, such as Disfan1’s
    table set and Nuclear Fish’s Particle Effects set that have specific
    installation instructions in them. Not following them can lead to hours of
    wasted time trying to get the set to work.</para>

    <para>Only after all of this work is done place the folder with the
    necessary files in your
    <filename>&lt;RCT3&nbsp;dir&gt;\Style\Themed</filename> folder. Simply
    copy and paste it into there. The set should be installed and accessible
    when you start up RCT3 next.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Common Errors</title>

    <section>
      <title>Game appears to hang</title>

      <para>On many errors the game appears to hang. This is caused by a
      normal <application>Windows</application> message hidden behind the
      game's graphic screen. Use <keycombo>
          <keycap function="alt">Alt</keycap>

          <keycap function="tab">Tab</keycap>
        </keycombo> to get to your <application>Windows</application> desktop
      and see the actual error message.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The vaunted <quote>no :siv: for :sid:</quote> error</title>

      <para>This error simply states that there was an incorrect installation.
      The culprit, almost every single time is having an extra folder hiding
      the scenery items from being accessed by the game. Simply remove the
      outer folder (do <emphasis>NOT RENAME THE INNER FOLDER</emphasis>) and
      the set should run.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The scenery does not appear in game</title>

      <para>If the scenery does not appear in game,</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure <emphasis>ALL</emphasis> of the scenery filters are
          enabled.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure you looked everywhere and not only where you expect
          it to be. For example old sets are often found among the
          walls.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you had RCT3 runnig when you installed the set, restart it.
          Sometimes it's possible to install CS when RCT3 is running, but
          sometimes it doesn't work.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure it is installed in the correct place, namely
          <filename>&lt;RCT3 dir&gt;\Style\Themed</filename>. If the set was
          distributed as an executable installer it is possible that it
          created another directory with or without the ® symbol in the
          <filename>Program Files/Atari</filename> folder (as mentioned above
          <application>Gold!</application> and non-US users are particularly
          vulnerable to this) and the CS got installed in the wrong
          directory.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><quote>You do not have sufficient access rights to
      open…</quote></title>

      <para>This problem is currently (14.12.2006) exclusive (to my knowledge)
      to Nuclear Fish’s Particle Effects pack. It is a result of improper
      installation. Read the enclosed ReadMe or his thread on the Atari forums
      for the solution to this problem which usually is a result of incorrect
      installation of the particle effects of the set. (thanks to ckfour for
      the pic :-P)</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>You have two copies of the set running in the game, but only one
      folder with the files in your
      <filename>&lt;RCT3&nbsp;dir&gt;\Style\Themed</filename> folder</title>

      <para>This is a simple issue from incorrect installation and an
      unfinished fix. This problem is a result of the nested folder issue but
      with a twist; the set was later correctly installed without removing the
      incorrect folder. Due to the way the game analyzes the
      <filename>.ovl</filename> files, two options are created in the RCT3
      menu. To fix this problem, just remove the redundant, nested
      folder.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>