<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Installing Custom Scenery</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>7.1.2007</date>

    <author>
      <surname>Coinich</surname>
    </author>

    <editor>
      <surname>Belgabor</surname>
    </editor>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>Installing Custom Scenery is not a difficult task. There are a few
  things to consider though, for example what file extension the pack has
  among other things. Here is a walkthrough for those who need help.</para>

  <important>
    <para>In the following tutorial <filename>&lt;RCT3 dir&gt;</filename> will
    be used as a placeholder for the directory you installed RCT3 to. Most
    commonly this is</para>

    <para><filename>C:\Program&nbsp;Files\Atari\RollerCoaster®&nbsp;Tycoon&nbsp;3</filename></para>

    <para>but that may differ on international versions or maybe
    <application>RCT3 Gold!</application> or <application>RCT3
    Platinum!</application> (or when you installed it to a custom directory).
    One thing you might easily miss is that some verisons leave out the
    trademark sign and it looks like this:</para>

    <para><filename>C:\Program&nbsp;Files\Atari\RollerCoaster&nbsp;Tycoon&nbsp;3</filename></para>
  </important>

  <para>For the less savvy in computer terms, <quote>folder</quote> and
  <quote>directory</quote> are the same and are used interchangably in this
  tutorial.</para>

  <section id="sect1">
    <title>Downloading Custom Scenery</title>

    <para>The first thing you need to know is how to get Custom Scenery, or
    <acronym>CS</acronym> for short.</para>

    <para>Your first stop in your quest for <acronym>CS</acronym> should be
    the <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/forumdisplay.php?f=406">Custom
    Scenery forum</ulink> on the <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/index.php">Atari®
    Community</ulink>. Most <acronym>CS</acronym> creators post about their
    sets there and inform you where and how to download and install them.
    There is also a <ulink
    url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/showthread.php?t=549086">stickied
    list of all <acronym>CS</acronym></ulink> in this forum.</para>

    <para>Often these sets are hosted on a third-party uploader, such as
    Rapidshare or Megaupload. Both options have free downloading capability
    and good sets can remain in storage indefinitely.</para>

    <para>Another option is to download sets from private servers hosted by
    many people from around the world. One thing to keep in mind though, is
    that some of these servers require registration before you download any
    objects. Here is a list of some popular CS hosting sites:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>CSO Database <ulink
        url="http://cso.rct-net.de/index.php?lang=1">English</ulink> / <ulink
        url="http://cso.rct-net.de/">German</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://modstothemax.net/community/">ModsToTheMax</ulink> (free
        registration required)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.rctrevalutions.com/forums/index.php?showforum=175">RCT
        Revalutions</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/news.php">Vodhin's Community
        Pages</ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://www.vodhin.net/RCT3Community/download.php?list.3">CS
        Download section</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <important>
      <para>It's suggested to download sets to a folder you create especially
      for this purpose (e.g. on your desktop). You can have subfolders within
      that folder that contain unopened sets and keep the original downloads
      if the set becomes corrupt for some reason.</para>

      <para>Do NOT download in to <filename>&lt;RCT3&nbsp;dir&gt;</filename>
      or any subfolder! This can lead to trouble.</para>
    </important>
  </section>

  <section id="sect2">
    <title>Unpacking and Installing Custom Scenery</title>

    <para>Once you have downloaded the set, you need to unpack it.</para>

    <para>There are three main formats that <acronym>CS</acronym> sets are
    released in.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The most common is in the <filename>.zip</filename> format and
        can be unzipped by most computers without having to download any extra
        software. If you do need software, you can use the same one as
        suggested for the <filename>.rar</filename> format in point 2.
        Occasionally, you might find a set that is an executable packaged as a
        <filename>.zip</filename> for memory reasons. Just unzip it and refer
        to point 3.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The next most common is the <filename>.rar</filename> format,
        which requires 3rd party software (e.g. <ulink
        url="http://www.rarlab.com/"><application>WinRAR</application>
        (shareware)</ulink> or <ulink
        url="http://www.7-zip.org/"><application>7-zip</application>
        (freeware)</ulink>) to unpack. Only a few sets, such as MaxInfinity’s
        Gothic Wall set, are packaged as <filename>.rar</filename>
        files.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The third format is in the form of a downloaded executable file.
        Only a few sets are provided in this manner. You just need to run it.
        In some cases the set gets installed to the wrong directory. Refer to
        <xref linkend="sect34" />.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The best place to unpack your downloaded <acronym>CS</acronym> sets
    is to a folder you create for that porpose (e.g. a subfolder in your
    <acronym>CS</acronym> download folder). Do <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> unpack
    your <acronym>CS</acronym> sets directly into the
    <filename>&lt;RCT3&nbsp;dir&gt;\Style\Themed</filename> folder as this is
    the leading cause of errors.</para>

    <important>
      <para>Whatever method/program you use to unpack the
      <acronym>CS</acronym> set, make sure it preserves the directory
      structure.</para>

      <para>Very Important: Do <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> rename anything you
      extracted! If you do, the set will almost certainly not work!</para>
    </important>

    <para>Before continuing, check to see if a ReadMe is present somewhere in
    the extracted folders. If so, <emphasis>READ IT!</emphasis> There are a
    few sets, such as Disfan1’s table set and Nuclear Fish’s Particle Effects
    set that have specific installation instructions in them. Not following
    them can lead to hours of wasted time trying to get the set to
    work.</para>

    <para>Now you need to identify the set directory. Look through the folder
    structure of the set to find the files
    <filename>style.common.ovl</filename> and
    <filename>style.unique.ovl</filename>. <emphasis role="bold">The directory
    that contains both files is the set directory</emphasis>. Normally this
    directory only contains these two files and one or more subdirectories.
    Also usually this directory is found directly in the folder you extracted
    the set to.</para>

    <para>Let's take a look at The_Cook's Cliff Face Set as an example. I
    assume you extracted it to <filename>C:\RCT3sets\temp</filename>. You'll
    find the following directory structure (leaving out unimportant stuff
    before the temp folder):</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>C:\RCT3sets</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>temp</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Examples</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>CliffFace_1sqStraight.dat</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>CliffFace_1sqStraight2.dat</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>CliffFace_2sqCorner.dat</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>...</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Rockface</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>r</para>

                    <itemizedlist>
                      <listitem>
                        <para>rock_d10.common.ovl</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>rock_d10.unique.ovl</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>rock_d11.common.ovl</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>...</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>style.common.ovl</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>style.unique.ovl</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Readme.txt</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The set directory in this case in the <filename>Rockface</filename>
    folder. Note that this set is not a perfect example, as it containes a
    readme file which you should have read and followed the instructions in
    :-)</para>

    <para>After identifying the set directory, copy or move it to your
    <filename>&lt;RCT3&nbsp;dir&gt;\Style\Themed</filename> folder.</para>

    <important>
      <para>Copy or move the directory, not only the contained files!</para>
    </important>

    <para> The set should be installed and accessible when you start up RCT3
    next.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="sect3">
    <title>Common Errors</title>

    <section id="sect31">
      <title>Game appears to hang</title>

      <para>On many errors, the game appears to hang. This is caused by a
      normal <application>Windows</application> message hidden behind the
      game's graphic screen. Use <keycombo>
          <keycap function="alt">Alt</keycap>

          <keycap function="tab">Tab</keycap>
        </keycombo> to get to your <application>Windows</application> desktop
      and see the actual error message.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sect32">
      <title>The game really hangs</title>

      <para>That means <keycombo>
          <keycap function="alt">Alt</keycap>

          <keycap function="tab">Tab</keycap>
        </keycombo> didn't work. This is usually caused by the so-called
      shadow bug. A few sets have very big <acronym>CS</acronym> items that
      trigger a bug in RCT3. If you want to use those, you need to turn off
      shadows in the RCT3 display options (refer to your RCT3
      handbook).</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sect33">
      <title>The vaunted <quote>no :svd: for :sid:</quote> error</title>

      <para>This error simply states that there was an incorrect installation.
      The culprit, almost every single time is having an extra folder hiding
      the scenery items from being accessed by the game. Simply remove the
      outer folder (do <emphasis>NOT RENAME THE INNER FOLDER</emphasis>) and
      the set should run.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sect34">
      <title>The scenery does not appear in game</title>

      <para>If the scenery does not appear in game,</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure <emphasis>ALL</emphasis> of the scenery filters are
          enabled.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure you looked everywhere and not only where you expect
          it to be. For example old sets are often found among the
          walls.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you had RCT3 running when you installed the set, restart
          it. Sometimes it's possible to install CS when RCT3 is running, but
          sometimes it doesn't work.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure it is installed in the correct place, namely
          <filename>&lt;RCT3 dir&gt;\Style\Themed</filename>. If the set was
          distributed as an executable installer it is possible that it
          created another directory with or without the ® symbol in the
          <filename>Program Files/Atari</filename> folder (as mentioned above
          <application>Gold!</application> and non-US users are particularly
          vulnerable to this) and the <acronym>CS</acronym> got installed in
          the wrong directory.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Wrong Directory</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="installation11.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="sect35">
      <title><quote>You do not have sufficient access rights to
      open…</quote></title>

      <para>This problem is currently (14.12.2006) exclusive (to my knowledge)
      to Nuclear Fish’s Particle Effects pack. It is a result of improper
      installation. Read the enclosed ReadMe or his thread on the Atari forums
      for the solution to this problem which usually is a result of incorrect
      installation of the particle effects of the set. (thanks to ckfour for
      the pic :-P)</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Access Rights Error</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="installation9.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="sect36">
      <title>You have two copies of the set running in the game, but only one
      folder with the files in your
      <filename>&lt;RCT3&nbsp;dir&gt;\Style\Themed</filename> folder</title>

      <para>This is usually the result of a failed installation you didn't fix
      completely, namely you didn't (completely) delete the wrong install. The
      <filename>style.common.ovl</filename> and
      <filename>style.unique.ovl</filename> files are still present in the
      wrong folder. Due to the way the game analyzes the
      <filename>.ovl</filename> files, two options are created in the RCT3
      menu. To fix this problem, remove the set completely and reinstall
      it.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="sect4">
    <title>Set Specific Problems</title>

    <section id="sect41">
      <title>Nuclear Fish's Particle Effect Set</title>

      <para>This set requires some particle files placed in a specific folder.
      The enclosed readme file explains this in detail, read it
      thoroughly!</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sect42">
      <title>Disfan1’s Tables Set</title>

      <para>This set is assembled in a method that does not follow current
      conventions. Open the unzipped file and copy <emphasis>ALL</emphasis>
      files to the <filename>&lt;RCT3&nbsp;dir&gt;\Style\Themed</filename>
      folder to get this to work. This information is also in it's ReadMe
      file.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sect43">
      <title>MaxInfinity’s DC Wall Set</title>

      <para>This set has been known to generate an error during the loading of
      RCT3 about an offset. The error message should look like this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Error in DC Wall Set</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="installation14.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>This error is nothing to worry about; just press Ok and the set
      and game will load normally.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="sect5">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>

    <section>
      <title>from Coinich</title>

      <para>I just wanted to thank all of the people who made CS possible
      here, including Belgabor and JonWil. These people, among many, have
      explored the horizons of Custom Scenery and have made this all
      possible.</para>

      <para>Thanks.</para>

      <para>I also wanted to thank all of the people out there who have helped
      me in the past install CS. It is an often asked question that can get
      quite tiring to answer, and I thank all who have written similar guides
      for different sites as I can finally understand the work they did to put
      such guides on the net.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>from Belgabor</title>

      <para>Thanks to Coinich for writing this tutorial.</para>

      <para>Sorry to Coinich for taking so long to edit it =)</para>

      <para>Also sorry for editing it so much (do you still recognize it?
      :-p), but I want this to be as clear, concise and thorough as possible,
      a goal I have hopefully achieved (If not, please recommend changes on
      the <ulink
      url="http://www.ataricommunity.com/forums/forumdisplay.php?f=406">Atari
      Forum</ulink>). I originally said I want to have lots of pictures in
      this tutorial (which Coinich provided), but editing it I started to
      think that this was rather more distracting than useful so I left most
      out, sorry again Coinich =)</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Credits</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The docbook css used for the html version of this document is
        based upon the one created by <ulink
        url="http://www.karakas-online.de">Chris Karakas</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>This CSS stylesheet uses <ulink
        url="http://www.matterform.com/qbullets/index.php">QBullets</ulink> in
        links. Thanks to Matterform Media for providing QBullets for free. If
        you plan to use them on your website, please observe the <ulink
        url="http://www.matterform.com/qbullets/usage.html">QBullets usage
        terms</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para role="matterform"><ulink
    url="http://www.matterform.com/"><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="/images/qb_credit.gif" scale="100" scalefit="0" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></ulink></para>

    <para><ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/"><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="http://sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=181524&amp;type=4" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="pdf">
          <imagedata fileref="/images/sflogo.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="chm">
          <imagedata fileref="/images/sflogo.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></ulink></para>
  </section>
</article>