<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Roller Coaster Tycoon® 3 Importer v18</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <date>13.7.2008</date>
    <author>
      <surname>Belgabor</surname>
    </author>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright (C) 2008 Belgabor, some rights reserved.</para>
      <para>This work is licensed under a <ulink
      url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons
      Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ulink>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>
  <xi:include href="general.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
              xpointer="element(/1)" />
  <section>
    <title>Proper transparency</title>
    <para>After a very long time I now found out how to do proper transparency
    and, as far as possible, got rid of the X-ray effect. By <quote>as far as
    possible</quote> I mean that after lots of experiments I came to the
    conclusion that for some objects you cannot fully prevent X-ray (even some
    original game objects show X-ray if you look closely). Still I think that
    the X-ray left is a lot less severe than before, it seems to only affect
    the object itself and then (probably) only parts of the same mesh. It also
    seems to occur mostly looking at the object from the left, provided you
    didn't rotate it. Left is in relation from your original view when you
    start a sandbox (ie looking at the entrace from inside the park. As to
    when this X-ray occurs I can give no good explanation. In general I'd say
    the more complex the object is, the likelier it is to occur. It may also
    include some unknown voodoo. If your object shows it, I've provided a few
    customization options that may help or not. To understand them, I first
    need to explain how proper transparency in RCT3 works.</para>
    <para>Meshes are stored in OVLs in two data chunks, one contains a list of
    all the vertices and the other the faces (triangles) as three indices into
    the vertex list. For transparent objects, the ovl file stores the face
    list three times, each one sorted along one axis. Now the crux is how the
    faces need to be sorted. From original ovls it seems to me that only the
    lowest coordinate (in the sorted direction) of the triangle matters. Still
    I have implemented several sorting algorithms that take other things into
    account. You can only influence the triangle sorting mechanism in ovlmake
    (see respective readme), the Importer normally uses the default
    <quote>minmax</quote> algorithm.</para>
    <para>RCT3 knows three transparency modes, none, masked and regular. The
    importer sets this automatically accorting to the texture style, so there
    is no reason for you to change it (although you can do so in the
    <guilabel>Transparency</guilabel> column). If it doesn't match the texture
    style, the importer displays it in red.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Trees, or manipulating normals</title>
    <para>If you have tried to create trees or plants with foliage, you may
    have noticed that lighting seems to be different from the ones in the
    game. This works by forcing the mesh normals of foliage to point straight
    upwards (Credit goes to TNStickBoy70 for discovering this) and you can do
    this by setting the <guilabel>Normals</guilabel> column to + whatever axis
    points up in your model (usually matching your coordinate system).</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title><application>MilkShape</application> support</title>
    <para>The Importer now reads the comments for various things from ms3d
    files and uses them to automatically fill some information for scenery.
    This only works if you load a ms3d file as a scenery file.</para>
    <note>
      <para>MilkShape indexes animation keyframes by frame index, starting at
      1. RCT3 uses time codes starting at 0. The Importer manages this, but
      you need to keep in mind that if you want a keyframe to occur after 1
      second, you need to set it at frame 31 in MilkShape (it uses 30 fps by
      default, which you should keep as RCT3 does as well).</para>
    </note>
    <section>
      <title>Model comment</title>
      <para>The model comment is the most complex and therefore uses a simple
      xml syntax. I won't go into much detail at them moment, so I'll just
      gine you an example and add a few brief notes.</para>
      <programlisting>&lt;ms3d&gt;
  &lt;name&gt;TestObject&lt;/name&gt;
  &lt;animation&gt;testobject_anim_rest&lt;/animation&gt;
  &lt;animation frame="1"&gt;testobject_anim_start&lt;/animation&gt;
  &lt;animation frame="120"&gt;testobject_anim_run&lt;/animation&gt;
  &lt;lod name="vlod" distance="200"&gt;
    &lt;mesh&gt;Base&lt;/mesh&gt;
    &lt;mesh&gt;AnimatedStuff_Hi&lt;/mesh&gt;
    &lt;bone&gt;parent&lt;/bone&gt;
    &lt;bone&gt;child&lt;/bone&gt;
  &lt;/lod&gt;
  &lt;lod name="vlod" distance="4000"&gt;
    &lt;mesh&gt;Base&lt;/mesh&gt;
    &lt;mesh&gt;AnimatedStuff_Low&lt;/mesh&gt;
    &lt;bone&gt;parent&lt;/bone&gt;
    &lt;bone&gt;child&lt;/bone&gt;
  &lt;/lod&gt;
&lt;/ms3d&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>The <emphasis>animation</emphasis> element(s) name(s) the
      animation(s) in the Importer. The <emphasis>frame</emphasis> attribute
      can be used to split the MilkShape animation into multiple animations in
      the importer (the number is a MilkShape frame index, so the example uses
      the first frame alone as the rest animation and as first frame of the
      start animation).</para>
      <para>The <emphasis>lod</emphasis> element defines both models and LODs
      that use them. The syntax should be obvious from the example. The bone
      names you need to use are the redefined ones (see <xref
      linkend="s_joint_comment" />).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Group comment</title>
      <para>The group comment is a list of whitespace delimited simple tags
      defining mesh settings (I recommend using newlines to separate, ie one
      per line).</para>
      <para>Tags you can use:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ds</emphasis> or <emphasis>doublesided</emphasis>
          Makes the mesh double-sided.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A flags tag (<emphasis>sign</emphasis>,
          <emphasis>terrain</emphasis>, <emphasis>cliff</emphasis>,
          <emphasis>water</emphasis>, <emphasis>watermask</emphasis>,
          <emphasis>billboard</emphasis> or
          <emphasis>animatedbillboard</emphasis>)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A texture style (e.g. <emphasis>SIOpaque</emphasis>,
          <emphasis>SIAlpha</emphasis>)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Material comment</title>
      <para>The material comment is a list of whitespace delimited simple tags
      defining texture settings (I recommend using newlines to separate, ie
      one per line).</para>
      <para>Tags you can use:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>recol</emphasis> Sets the texture recolourable.
          Needs to be followed by a tag consisting of the texture choices, 1
          for first, 2 for second and 3 for third. These need to be in order
          (e.g. to activate all choices, use <quote>recol 123</quote>).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ref</emphasis> Marks the texture as being
          referenced, i.e. it will not be automatically added. Needs to be
          followed either by the texture ovl reference path (may not contain
          space characters) or <quote>-</quote>. In the first case the
          Importer will add the reference path automatically to the reference
          list. Use the second one if you have already defined the path on a
          different material or want to add it manually later. Example:
          <quote>ref ../shared/prefixsSet-textures</quote>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="s_joint_comment">
      <title>Joint comment</title>
      <para>The joint comment consists of a single tag defining a new name for
      the joint. <application>MilkShape</application> has a limit of 32
      characters for joint names, so if you need more (e.g. for effect bones),
      use this feature.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title><application>Blender</application></title>
    <para>Please refer to the readme coming with the
    <application>Blender</application> scripts.</para>
  </section>
</article>