<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Roller Coaster Tycoon® 3 Importer v18</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>13.7.2008</date>

    <author>
      <surname>Belgabor</surname>
    </author>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright (C) 2008 Belgabor, some rights reserved.</para>

      <para>This work is licensed under a <ulink
      url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons
      Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ulink>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <xi:include href="general.xml" xpointer="element(/1)"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <section>
    <title>Change log</title>

    <para>As the importer and ovlmake use a common importing and model
    read/treatment engine, I'll usually release both at once. Since documents
    can apply to both, it's a bit troubresome to get all the versions
    straight, so every published package will now list a svn revision in its
    file name. Using this revision number, you can see what belongs together.
    In the case of documentation or supplementary scripts, the number might
    also be higher than that of the <application>importer</application> or
    <application>ovlmake</application> package to denote corrections done
    after, as long as no new
    <application>importer</application>/<application>ovlmake</application>
    pack is out, they still apply to the latest one.</para>

    <para>In the following change log, the <quote>Engine</quote> section
    describes changes in the mentioned engine and therefore affect both the
    <application>Importer</application> and
    <application>ovlmake</application>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Importer v18b2 / ovlmake v0.5 (svn130)</title>

      <section>
        <title>Engine</title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Partial workaround for the 31 mesh limit. Meshes
            with the same settings will be merged on import.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Support for bone weights and meshes assigned to more
            than one bone</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Option to automatically update from model fires
            and/or sort bones</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Reject Blender default animation, bone, texture and
            spline names</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Sense of rotation matrices corrected for right
            handed coordinate system</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Animation import from ms3d</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Crash on broken modxml</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Rare-occurring bug that lead to creation of broken
            ovls</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Cleaned] Fixed a lot of compiler warnings </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><application>Importer</application></title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Right double-click on A to re-auto model bones
            without confirmation</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Toggle for the animation display on LODs</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Detect Problems menu command to find some issues
            that can lead to a 60% crash or a no sid for svd.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] More visual flags</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Some support for moving theme files around. The
            importer is able to fix the paths of all files if the directory
            structure did not change.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Busy notice while loading or saving scenery
            files.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] When changing a bone name in a model window, ask the
            user if he wants to change the name in other animated models or
            animations.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Show selected item in list boxes after update</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Load error for empty matrix stacks</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Prefix missing on returned filename if creating from
            scenery settings dialog</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Clear prefix when loading old scn file</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Make auto coordinate system from file button work.
            Also gives somewhat helpful suggestion when no coordinate system
            information is available.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Up/down spin controls no longer activated if nothing
            is selected</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Bugs when trying to load broken modxml files.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] OK and Cancel buttons hidden in bone settings window
            if the assigend meshes list was too long.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Prevent errors due to size in squares being set to
            more than 1.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Update parents of bones when changing the parent's
            name.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Removed] The fix orientation matrix is now gone for good as
            it created a lot of confusion. That removes the use of a default
            matrix, so that's gone as well.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><application>ovlmake</application></title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Support for multi-chunk and multi-animation
            flats</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Support for binding sound to scenery</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Support for custom sound</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Added] Brief message output format, mostly for evaluation
            by front-ends</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Changed] Error report system to give as much error
            information as available</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>[Fixed] Spelling mistakes</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Proper transparency</title>

    <para>After a very long time I now found out how to do proper transparency
    and, as far as possible, got rid of the X-ray effect. By <quote>as far as
    possible</quote> I mean that after lots of experiments I came to the
    conclusion that for some objects you cannot fully prevent X-ray (even some
    original game objects show X-ray if you look closely). Still I think that
    the X-ray left is a lot less severe than before, it seems to only affect
    the object itself and then (probably) only parts of the same mesh. It also
    seems to occur mostly looking at the object from the left, provided you
    didn't rotate it. Left is in relation from your original view when you
    start a sandbox (ie looking at the entrace from inside the park. As to
    when this X-ray occurs I can give no good explanation. In general I'd say
    the more complex the object is, the likelier it is to occur. It may also
    include some unknown voodoo. If your object shows it, I've provided a few
    customization options that may help or not. To understand them, I first
    need to explain how proper transparency in RCT3 works.</para>

    <para>Meshes are stored in OVLs in two data chunks, one contains a list of
    all the vertices and the other the faces (triangles) as three indices into
    the vertex list. For transparent objects, the ovl file stores the face
    list three times, each one sorted along one axis. Now the crux is how the
    faces need to be sorted. From original ovls it seems to me that only the
    lowest coordinate (in the sorted direction) of the triangle matters. Still
    I have implemented several sorting algorithms that take other things into
    account. You can only influence the triangle sorting mechanism in ovlmake
    (see respective readme), the Importer normally uses the default
    <quote>minmax</quote> algorithm.</para>

    <para>RCT3 knows three transparency modes, none, masked and regular. The
    importer sets this automatically accorting to the texture style, so there
    is no reason for you to change it (although you can do so in the
    <guilabel>Transparency</guilabel> column). If it doesn't match the texture
    style, the importer displays it in red.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Trees, or manipulating normals</title>

    <para>If you have tried to create trees or plants with foliage, you may
    have noticed that lighting seems to be different from the ones in the
    game. This works by forcing the mesh normals of foliage to point straight
    upwards (Credit goes to TNStickBoy70 for discovering this) and you can do
    this by setting the <guilabel>Normals</guilabel> column to + whatever axis
    points up in your model (usually matching your coordinate system).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><application>MilkShape</application> support</title>

    <para>The Importer now reads the comments for various things from ms3d
    files and uses them to automatically fill some information for scenery.
    This only works if you load a ms3d file as a scenery file.</para>

    <note>
      <para>MilkShape indexes animation keyframes by frame index, starting at
      1. RCT3 uses time codes starting at 0. The Importer manages this, but
      you need to keep in mind that if you want a keyframe to occur after 1
      second, you need to set it at frame 31 in MilkShape (it uses 30 fps by
      default, which you should keep as RCT3 does as well).</para>
    </note>

    <section>
      <title>Model comment</title>

      <para>The model comment is the most complex and therefore uses a simple
      xml syntax. I won't go into much detail at them moment, so I'll just
      gine you an example and add a few brief notes.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;ms3d&gt;
  &lt;name&gt;TestObject&lt;/name&gt;
  &lt;animation&gt;testobject_anim_rest&lt;/animation&gt;
  &lt;animation frame="1"&gt;testobject_anim_start&lt;/animation&gt;
  &lt;animation frame="120"&gt;testobject_anim_run&lt;/animation&gt;
  &lt;lod name="vlod" distance="200"&gt;
    &lt;mesh&gt;Base&lt;/mesh&gt;
    &lt;mesh&gt;AnimatedStuff_Hi&lt;/mesh&gt;
    &lt;bone&gt;parent&lt;/bone&gt;
    &lt;bone&gt;child&lt;/bone&gt;
  &lt;/lod&gt;
  &lt;lod name="vlod" distance="4000"&gt;
    &lt;mesh&gt;Base&lt;/mesh&gt;
    &lt;mesh&gt;AnimatedStuff_Low&lt;/mesh&gt;
    &lt;bone&gt;parent&lt;/bone&gt;
    &lt;bone&gt;child&lt;/bone&gt;
  &lt;/lod&gt;
&lt;/ms3d&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The <emphasis>animation</emphasis> element(s) name(s) the
      animation(s) in the Importer. The <emphasis>frame</emphasis> attribute
      can be used to split the MilkShape animation into multiple animations in
      the importer (the number is a MilkShape frame index, so the example uses
      the first frame alone as the rest animation and as first frame of the
      start animation).</para>

      <para>The <emphasis>lod</emphasis> element defines both models and LODs
      that use them. The syntax should be obvious from the example. The bone
      names you need to use are the redefined ones (see <xref
      linkend="s_joint_comment" />).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Group comment</title>

      <para>The group comment is a list of whitespace delimited simple tags
      defining mesh settings (I recommend using newlines to separate, ie one
      per line).</para>

      <para>Tags you can use:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ds</emphasis> or <emphasis>doublesided</emphasis>
          Makes the mesh double-sided.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A flags tag (<emphasis>sign</emphasis>,
          <emphasis>terrain</emphasis>, <emphasis>cliff</emphasis>,
          <emphasis>water</emphasis>, <emphasis>watermask</emphasis>,
          <emphasis>billboard</emphasis> or
          <emphasis>animatedbillboard</emphasis>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A texture style (e.g. <emphasis>SIOpaque</emphasis>,
          <emphasis>SIAlpha</emphasis>)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Material comment</title>

      <para>The material comment is a list of whitespace delimited simple tags
      defining texture settings (I recommend using newlines to separate, ie
      one per line).</para>

      <para>Tags you can use:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>recol</emphasis> Sets the texture recolourable.
          Needs to be followed by a tag consisting of the texture choices, 1
          for first, 2 for second and 3 for third. These need to be in order
          (e.g. to activate all choices, use <quote>recol 123</quote>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ref</emphasis> Marks the texture as being
          referenced, i.e. it will not be automatically added. Needs to be
          followed either by the texture ovl reference path (may not contain
          space characters) or <quote>-</quote>. In the first case the
          Importer will add the reference path automatically to the reference
          list. Use the second one if you have already defined the path on a
          different material or want to add it manually later. Example:
          <quote>ref ../shared/prefixsSet-textures</quote>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="s_joint_comment">
      <title>Joint comment</title>

      <para>The joint comment consists of a single tag defining a new name for
      the joint. <application>MilkShape</application> has a limit of 32
      characters for joint names, so if you need more (e.g. for effect bones),
      use this feature.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><application>Blender</application></title>

    <para>Please refer to the readme coming with the
    <application>Blender</application> scripts.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Credits</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/3.0/88x31.png"
                         scale="100" scalefit="0" />
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject></ulink>This work is licensed under a <ulink
        url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative
        Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Atari® and Roller Coaster Tycoon 3® are trademarks of Atari Inc.
        All Rights Reserved.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The docbook css used for the html version of this document is
        based upon the one created by <ulink
        url="http://www.karakas-online.de">Chris Karakas</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>This CSS stylesheet uses <ulink
        url="http://www.matterform.com/qbullets/index.php">QBullets</ulink> in
        links. Thanks to Matterform Media for providing QBullets for free. If
        you plan to use them on your website, please observe the <ulink
        url="http://www.matterform.com/qbullets/usage.html">QBullets usage
        terms</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para role="matterform"><ulink
    url="http://www.matterform.com/"><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="/images/qb_credit.gif" scale="100" scalefit="0" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></ulink></para>

    <para><ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/"><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="http://sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=181524&amp;type=4" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="pdf">
          <imagedata fileref="/images/sflogo.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="chm">
          <imagedata fileref="/images/sflogo.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></ulink></para>
  </section>
</article>
