<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article class="whitepaper" revision="1.0">
  <title>Beginner's Tutorial for the RCT3 Custom Scenery Importer</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>12.11.2006</date>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1</revnumber>

        <date>14.11.2006</date>

        <author>
          <surname>Belgabor</surname>
        </author>

        <revdescription>
          <para>Initial version for v16fix4</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>2</revnumber>

        <date>29.11.2006</date>

        <author>
          <surname>Belgabor</surname>
        </author>

        <revdescription>
          <para>Update for v16fix5</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>3</revnumber>

        <date>20.12.2006</date>

        <author>
          <surname>Belgabor</surname>
        </author>

        <revdescription>
          <para>Update for v17</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>

      <revision>
        <revnumber>4</revnumber>

        <date>7.1.2007</date>

        <author>
          <surname>Belgabor</surname>
        </author>

        <revdescription>
          <para>Update for v17fix1</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <author>
      <surname>Belgabor</surname>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <tocchap>
    <tocentry></tocentry>
  </tocchap>

  <para>This tutorial will lead you through the steps required to import your
  first object into <application>Roller Coaster Tycoon 3</application>®. Only
  the options and steps required for a basic import will be explained, do not
  expect to hear about everything you can do with it.</para>

  <para>This also means that <emphasis>all of these steps</emphasis> are
  required!</para>

  <para>This document applies to the <application>RCT3 Importer</application>
  Version 17fix1.</para>

  <section id="sect1">
    <title>Preparing for the import</title>

    <para>This section will show you what you need to do before running the
    importer.</para>

    <section id="sect11">
      <title>Initial preparation</title>

      <para>While it may sound trivial, it's an important step to keep things
      organized: Create a directory on your hard disk that will hold your
      custom scenery sets. You should also create a subdirectory within for
      each set. Within each of those it is recommended to put each Custom
      Scenery (<acronym>CS</acronym>) object along with all belonging files
      into it's own subdirectory.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sect12">
      <title>Creating the 3D model</title>

      <para>This process is very much beyond the scope of this document. You
      need to get a suitable 3D modeller and read a few tutorials on how to
      use it. Here is a list of the modellers used most often for creating
      custom scenery for RCT3:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><application>3DStudio</application> /
          <application>3DSmax</application>. Very expensive professional 3D
          modeller. If you can get an academic license you might be able to
          afford it.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><application>MilkShape</application>. Cheap (25$) shareware
          with a 30 day trial period. Was the custom scenery creation tool of
          choice for a long time, but more and more try their hands on</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><application>Blender</application>. Free open source
          professional modeller. It's user interface is pretty non-standard
          and therefore requires a bit of patience to get used to. When you
          get acquainted to it you won't want to miss it anymore and
          <application>Blender</application> becomes a very powerful
          tool.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><application>SketchUp</application>. Comes in two versions,
          <application>Google SketchUp</application> (free) and
          <application>SketchUp Pro</application> (commercial, trial
          available). Very easy and intuitive to use. Current drawbacks are
          that it tends to create too many faces on round objects which can be
          hard to fix later. Another drawback is that SketchUp sometimes
          produces superfluous faces and edges which have to be cleaned up in
          <application>an other modeller</application> (more on faces below).
          A script to export directly from <application>SketchUp</application>
          to <filename>ASE</filename> can be found on <ulink
          url="http://belgabor.vodhin.net/software">Belgabor's software
          page</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For more detailed information and links to less commonly used
      modellers as well as modeller specific tutorials see <ulink
      url="http://belgabor.vodhin.net/software">Belgabor's software
      page</ulink>.</para>

      <para>For creating your models, you should keep the following guidelines
      in mind:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Keep your first model simple to get accustomed to the
          importing process. A simple cube works well for example.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Make your model the right size and position it correctly. A
          RCT3 square is usually 4x4 of your modellers units big (in
          <application>SketchUp</application> things are a bit more complex).
          For more information see <ulink
          url="http://belgabor.vodhin.net/facts">Belgabor's facts &amp;
          figures page</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Keep the number of faces as low as possible. A face<indexterm>
              <primary>face</primary>
            </indexterm> (also called <quote>poly</quote>, <quote>tri</quote>
          or <quote>triangle</quote>) is the smallest surface subunit of a
          model and the unit that causes <quote>work</quote> for the 3D engine
          of RCT3. Therefore the more faces your model has, the longer the
          engine needs to display your scenery item which may lead to lag. As
          a rule of thumb try to stay below 500 faces, even better below 300.
          Note that the engine uses triangular faces while most modern
          modellers can use at least quads (faces with four corners or
          vertices). These are converted to triangles in the export or
          conversion process, so the actual number of faces may be a lot
          higher than your modeller shows.</para>

          <para>Some tips on how to keep your face number low:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Make things only as round as necessary. Rounded parts
              usually use the most faces. As a rule of thumb never give a full
              circle more than 16 sections without good reason. If the part of
              the object is really thin, you might even get a good looking
              result with just three sections and keeping it welded (more on
              that below).</para>

              <para>The same applies to spheres. If possible use low iteration
              icospheres. Modellers can also create so-called uv-spheres.
              These use up more faces but are easier to uv-map (hence the
              name. More on uv-mapping below), so use them only if you need a
              complex texture on it.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Remove unnecessary invisible faces. If your model has
              invisible (inside) face1.3s due to the modelling process, remove
              them as they will use up processing power. Keep in mind that
              they may still affect lighting if their vertices are welded to
              visible faces, so it may be necessary to keep them in some cases
              (more on this below).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Consider using alpha textures. This is a rather advanced
              topic, but you should be aware of the possibility. If you want
              to create an object with a filigree see-through pattern (a
              railing or iron works for example), it may be easier for you and
              on the engine if you don't model the pattern but rather use a
              plane that has a see-through (alpha) texture assigned.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Weld</primary>
          </indexterm>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>Unweld</primary>
          </indexterm>

          <para>Selectively weld/unweld your model. To understand this topic
          you first have to understand how the RCT3 3D engine (and probably
          all other 3D engines as well) calculates the lighting of the object.
          For this the difference of the direction the light falls in (in RCT3
          the sun at day and lamps at night) and the direction of your
          objects' normals is used.</para>

          <para>Now you may ask what a normal is. Let's start with a face
          normal. You can imagine this as an arrow that points away form the
          face being perpendicular to it, so if compared to the direction the
          light comes in you get the angle under which it hits the face and it
          is possible to shade it accordingly.</para>

          <para>To make objects look more realistic, the 3D engine rather uses
          vertex normals. This concept is a bit harder to understand. The
          vertex normal is a property of the vertices (corners) of your object
          and represent the normal of the tangent plane of your object at that
          vertex. To understand what that means imagine your object as a real
          and put it on the top of your desk touching it only with one vertex.
          That (roughly) makes your desk the tangent plane of that vertex, so
          it's normal would point vertically to the floor in that position.
          Vertex normals are automatically calculated by your 3D modeller,
          usually as the mean of the face normals of all faces the vertex is
          part of.</para>

          <para>Here comes the concept of welded and unwelded vertices into
          play. Imagine the corner of a cube. Usually your modeller creates it
          welded. This means the corner is only one vertex which is used by
          the three faces that border it. If you unweld this vertex (How to do
          that depends on your modeller, search for
          <guilabel>Unweld</guilabel> or <guilabel>Unbind
          points/vertices</guilabel>) a copy of it is created for each face
          that uses it. In the example above the one corner vertex is replaced
          by three, one for (and used by) each face. If you think a bit about
          it you will realize what that means for the vertex normal(s). If the
          vertex is welded, its vertex normal will point away from the center
          of the cube and the engine of RCT3 will treat it as if the object
          was supposed to be round there. If the vertex is unwelded, each of
          the three vertices in it's place gets its own vertex normal. As each
          is only part of one face, its vertex normal is identical to the face
          normal. You may want to have a look at the weld/unweld section on
          <ulink url="http://belgabor.vodhin.net/facts">Belgabor's facts &amp;
          figures page</ulink> for some pictures about this. The take home
          message is you need to unweld vertices/edges if they are supposed to
          look <quote>pointy</quote>, if they are supposed to be round, keep
          them welded.</para>

          <para>Usually you cannot selectively unweld a vertex in regard to
          certain edges, you can only fully unweld it. If you want to keep
          some edges that it's part of welded, you need to first unweld it and
          then weld the vertices of the faces whose common edge you want to
          have welded. Note: How to weld depends again on your modeller, it
          can be a bit hard to find (for example it is called <guilabel>Remove
          Doubles</guilabel> in <application>Blender</application>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Usually you shouldn't bother using the 3D modeller's materials
          for your object. RCT3 and therefore the Importer can only used
          uv-mapped bitmap textures, while most modellers use procedural
          (calculated) textures. There are ways to make a bitmap texture form
          such procedural textures (usually called
          <guilabel>texture-baking</guilabel> or
          <guilabel>uv-baking</guilabel>), but usually they don't lead to a
          satisfactory result.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="sect13">
      <title>Obtaining a bitmap texture for your model</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Model Texture</primary>

          <secondary>Requirements</secondary>
        </indexterm>As stated above you need to use bitmap textures for your
      custom scenery 3D models. A further prerequisite for the final texture
      you'll use in the importer is that it has to be square and its width and
      height have to be a power of two (for example 64x64, 128x128 or
      256x256). Note that this size can have an effect on the objects load
      time and the amount of memory needed later in the game leading to lag,
      so don't make them bigger than necessary. I'd recommend to use 256x256.
      If you have a very detailed texture you could use 512x512. If your
      object is single-colored, even a 4x4 texture is enough (maybe even 1x1
      works, but I haven't tested that).</para>

      <para>The first (and hardest) option to obtain a texture is to draw it
      yourself using a bitmap editor like <application>Adobe
      Photoshop</application> or <application>The Gimp</application>. Even if
      you don't want to draw your own texture it is a good idea to have a
      bitmap editor around to resize or manipulate them.</para>

      <para>The second option is to find a suitable texture on the net. There
      are lots of free (and even more non-free) texture sites out there. One
      thing you should keep in mind is not to violate copyright. <emphasis>It
      is not necessary to say something is protected by copyright, copyright
      is automatic!</emphasis> So if a site doesn't explicitly say you are
      free to use images or textures on it, <emphasis>you may not</emphasis>.
      Also remember that symbols and brand names can be protected by copyright
      or trademark laws, so it's better not to use them. If you're annoyed by
      this, remember it protects you as well. So whatever
      <acronym>CS</acronym> you create, others may not host the set or rip
      your models or textures without your permission =)</para>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Model Texture</primary>

          <secondary>Creation Software</secondary>
        </indexterm>A third possibility is to use a special texture creation
      software. A good (and free) example is <application>Wood
      Workshop</application> by <ulink
      url="http://www.spiralgraphics.biz/index.htm">Spiral Graphics</ulink>,
      which is a tuned-down version of their commercial texture creator,
      <application>Genetica</application>. They also offer free texture packs
      which can be used with the <application>Genetica Viewer</application>
      (also free). There are also other texture creation software packages,
      just Google for them (and tell me if you find a good free one :-P
      ).</para>

      <para>In whatever way you get your texture, it is always good to get a
      seamless one. A seamless texture is a texture that doesn't have a
      visible rim if tiled (checkerboarded). This allows you a bit of
      sloppiness when uv-mapping or getting a more detailed looking model with
      a smaller actual texture size.</para>

      <para>You also should create an icon texture<indexterm>
          <primary>Icon texture</primary>

          <secondary>Creating</secondary>
        </indexterm> at this point. This is a bitmap that will hold menu icons
      for your theme. It has the same restrictions as a model texture, the
      only thing that is different is that you can (and should) use a
      <filename>PNG</filename> with transparency here, otherwise the
      alternating white/gray background will not show through. The standard
      size is 512x512 and usually 64x64 icons are set up. You don't need to
      create the final icons at this point, but at least a temporary icon
      texture is needed. Icons are later numbered starting at the top left,
      going right first and then down (like western writing).</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sect14">
      <title>UV-Mapping</title>

      <para><indexterm zone="sect14">
          <primary>UV-Mapping</primary>
        </indexterm>UV-Mapping is used to <quote>assign</quote> a (bitmap)
      texture to a model and is done inside your 3D modeller. I put
      <quote>assign</quote> in quotes since technically it's not correct. What
      you do is give the vertices of your model an additional set of
      coordinates (additional to its spacial x/y/z 3D coordinates) in
      so-called texture-space. These coordinates are called <quote>u</quote>
      and <quote>v</quote> (hence uv-mapping) or <quote>s</quote> and
      <quote>t</quote>. There is a difference between these two naming
      conventions but that doesn't need to concern you for creating custom
      scenery. You also should know that these coordinates are relative. That
      means 0 represents one end of the texture and 1 the other one, so the
      size of the texture you use for uv-mapping can differ from the one you
      use later in the importer, only the layout of the texture has to match
      (ie. don't mirror it).</para>

      <para>While this may sound complicated or strange, it just tells the
      model (and later the 3D engine) which part of the texture to use for
      which part (face) of your object. So what you should remember from the
      explanation in the previous paragraph is:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The uv-mapping is a property of your model and is therefore
          stored inside the 3D model file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You don't have to assign the same texture to the model in the
          importer that you used to uv-map.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>This also applies to the size.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>(Note for later: You always have to assign a texture in the
          importer, even if it's the same one you used to uv-map. The
          information which texture was used is <emphasis>not</emphasis>
          transferred to the importer.)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>As above for creating the model, here is a list of things to keep
      in mind about uv-mapping:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The exact process depends on your 3D modeller. Usually there
          are specific tutorials about uv-mapping for it.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Depending on the complexity of your model and texture,
          uv-mapping can be a very time-consuming process that can take you as
          long or even longer than creating your model.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>UV-map as exact as possible. Small errors can be very visible
          and annoying in your finished object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The texture is tiled in texture space, so if you map over the
          rim of it, it starts again from the opposing side. This will lead to
          a visible seam if your texture isn't seamless.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you need more than one basic texture for your object, you
          can put them all into one texture bitmap and uv-map the parts of
          your model to the correct part of your texture. This is common
          practice.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="sect15">
      <title>Coordinate system</title>

      <para>As long as you are still in your 3D modeller you should take note
      which <indexterm>
          <primary>Coordinate systems</primary>
        </indexterm>coordinate system it uses. We need two properties, which
      axis points up and its handedness. The first is easy, just have a look
      whether the x, y or z axis points up. The second is a bit more tricky. A
      coordinate system can be left or right-handed. Here is how to determine
      the handedness:</para>

      <note>
        <para>Using your right hand, point the thumb in the direction of the
        x-axis and your index finger in the direction of the y-axis (They
        should form a <quote>playing pistol</quote> or <quote>Five glasses of
        beer for the sawmill guys</quote> gesture). If you now can point your
        middle finger in the direction of the z-axis without hurting yourself
        (or over bending if you're flexible enough :-) ), it's a right-handed
        coordinate system.</para>
      </note>

      <para>In most cases you get a right-handed coordinate system.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sect16">
      <title>Converting the model</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Model</primary>

          <secondary>Converting</secondary>
        </indexterm>The importer only supports loading
      <filename>ASE</filename> and <filename>MS3D</filename> files at the
      moment. If you can directly save or export to one of these formats, do
      so and skip this section. If not, you need to convert your model to
      <filename>ASE</filename>. The free converter of choice is <ulink
      url="http://mirex.mypage.sk/index.php?selected=1"><application>Biturn</application></ulink>.
      Get it and convert you model to <filename>ASE</filename>
      (<application>3ds max</application> ASCII) format. It's not recommended
      to convert to <filename>MS3D</filename> format as
      <application>Biturn</application> is known to do strange coordinate
      system conversions when converting from <filename>MS3D</filename>, no
      one knows what it will do if you convert to
      <filename>MS3D</filename>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sect17">
      <title>Getting and installing the importer</title>

      <para>Maybe you already did this, if not, get the importer form the
      <ulink url="http://rct3.sourceforge.net">home page on
      sourceforge</ulink>. It is distributed as a <filename>ZIP</filename>
      file, put the contents into a directory of your choice. Updates should
      go into the same directory as some settings are stored inside a small
      file in this directory. Always make sure you overwrite all files when
      you update.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sect18">
      <title>A few notes on OVL files</title>

      <para>The <filename>OVL</filename> file format has been designed for
      <application>RCT3</application> by Frontier. You don't have to know
      everything about their internals, but there are a few things you have to
      know:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You <emphasis>may not</emphasis> change the name of an
          <filename>OVL</filename> file in the Windows Explorer. If you want
          to change the name you need to recreate it (see <xref
          linkend="sect224" />).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You <emphasis>may not</emphasis> change the name of any
          directory of your installed theme. If you want to change them you
          need to change the respective setting in the importer and
          reinstall.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you changed any file or directory name you have to delete
          any previously installed old version of your theme from Style/Themed
          (see <xref linkend="sect24" />).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="sect2">
    <title>Importing your first object</title>

    <para>At this point you should have installed the importer and prepared
    all necessary files (model, texture bitmap and icon bitmap).</para>

    <section id="sect21">
      <title>Primary setup</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Main Window</primary>
        </indexterm>After starting the importer you'll see the main window of
      the importer:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>RCT3 Custom Scenery Importer, Main Window</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="main.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The first thing you should decide is which theme type you want to
      give your set (1). This influences where it appears when a user filters
      the scenery by theme (the buttons at the top of the scenery menus). Note
      that the last four types only work if the user has Soaked! or Wild!
      installed.</para>

      <para>The next thing to decide is the prefix (2). This will be prepended
      to scenery <filename>OVL</filename> names and the set directory. It
      should identify you as the creator, so set it to your screen name or to
      an abbreviated form of it. You should also end it with a separator of
      some kind, recommended is a <userinput>-</userinput>. At this point you
      can also save this prefix, choose <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>

          <guisubmenu>Save Default Prefix</guisubmenu>
        </menuchoice> from the menu. If you do this you won't have to repeat
      this step for you next theme.</para>

      <important>
        <para>You can leave the prefix empty, but it is not recommended to do
        so. Scenery <filename>OVL</filename> names have to be unique, so if
        you don't set it and someone else publishes a custom scenery set that
        contains an object with the same name these will conflict. Using a
        unique prefix prevents that (or at least makes it rather
        unlikely).</para>
      </important>

      <para>Now enter the name for your theme (3). Together with the prefix
      this will form the name of the directory in Style\Themed where your set
      will be installed to. It is <emphasis>not</emphasis> displayed to the
      user in the game.</para>

      <note>
        <para>You can only use ASCII characters for the prefix and theme name.
        This is enforced as people with different international
        <application>Windows</application> versions may have trouble using
        your theme otherwise.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="sect22">
      <title>Create a scenery <filename>OVL</filename></title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Scenery OVL</primary>

          <secondary>Creating</secondary>
        </indexterm>Now it's time to create the first scenery ovl, so press
      the <guibutton>Create OVL</guibutton> button (7) in the main window.
      This will open the <guilabel>Create OVL</guilabel> window:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>RCT3 Custom Scenery Importer, Create OVL Window</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="createscenery.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Before continuing with the creation process let's take a look at
      how lists work in this window (and windows you open form it). All lists
      have a common interface. Some specific lists may lack certain elements
      or have more, but basically they all work the same. For example take a
      look at the texture list (4). At the top you can find an up/down control
      that allows you to change the order of the items. Below it there's a
      group of buttons that allow you to add a new item
      (<guibutton>+</guibutton>), edit it (<guibutton>E</guibutton>), copy it
      (<guibutton>C</guibutton>) or delete it (<guibutton>-</guibutton>). The
      flat <guibutton>C</guibutton> button will delete the whole list.
      <mousebutton>Double-clicking</mousebutton> on a list entry will usually
      perform the same action as selecting it and pressing the
      <guibutton>E</guibutton> edit button. Don't worry, all buttons will show
      a short help text when you hover the mouse cursor over them for a bit
      :-)</para>

      <para>Now lets start.</para>

      <section id="sect221">
        <title>Add the texture</title>

        <para><indexterm>
            <primary>Model Texture</primary>

            <secondary>Adding</secondary>
          </indexterm>First you have to add your model texture, so press the
        add button (<guibutton>+</guibutton>) in the texture list (4). This
        will open a file selection window, so go on and select your texture
        bitmap file and press <guibutton>Ok</guibutton>. You will then get the
        <guilabel>Add Texture</guilabel> window:</para>

        <figure>
          <title>RCT3 Custom Scenery Importer, Add Texture Window</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="texture.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The <guilabel>Texture Name</guilabel> (a) and <guilabel>Texture
        Filename</guilabel> (b) should be filled with the name and path to the
        texture file you chose. Basically there is nothing you need to change,
        although you can change the <guilabel>Texture Name</guilabel> (a) if
        you want to. When you're finished, press <guibutton>Ok</guibutton>
        (c). If you get an error message this usually means that something is
        wrong with your texture bitmap (review <xref linkend="sect13" />). Fix
        the problem and press <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> (c) again. If you need
        to change the file, press the <guibutton>Open</guibutton> button in
        (6) and select the correct one.</para>

        <note>
          <para>If you press <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> in the first file
          selection windo,w you get the <guilabel>Advanced Texture
          Settings</guilabel> window. This is not covered here.</para>
        </note>

        <para>After adding the texture it appears in the list (4).</para>
      </section>

      <section id="sect222">
        <title>Add the model</title>

        <para><indexterm>
            <primary>Model</primary>

            <secondary>Adding</secondary>
          </indexterm><indexterm>
            <primary>Model</primary>

            <secondary>Settings</secondary>
          </indexterm>Back in the <guilabel>Create OVL</guilabel> window,
        press the add button (<guibutton>+</guibutton>) in the model list (5).
        You will get the <guilabel>Model Settings</guilabel> window:</para>

        <figure>
          <title>RCT3 Custom Scenery Importer, Model Settings Window</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="model.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>First, press the <guibutton>...</guibutton> button (b) and
        select your model file. If you get an error, review <xref
        linkend="sect12" /> and/or <xref linkend="sect14" />. Before
        continuing, have a look at the group list on the right. If there are
        only dark red (maroon) entries (like the <guilabel>root</guilabel>
        entry (e)), you probably forgot to uv-map the model (review <xref
        linkend="sect14" />). After opening the file, the name (a) will be
        pre-filled based on the model file name, you can change it if you
        want.</para>

        <para>Now it's time to setup the model transformation matrix that will
        convert the model from the coordinate system your modeller uses to the
        one RCT3 uses. Use this table to find out which matrix is
        needed:</para>

        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Coordinate System</entry>

                <entry>Modeller</entry>

                <entry>Matrix</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Left-handed, Y-up</entry>

                <entry>Some
                <application>3DStudio</application>/<application>3DS
                max</application> versions</entry>

                <entry>(none)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Right-handed, Z-up</entry>

                <entry>Most 3d modellers (e.g.
                <application>Blender</application>)</entry>

                <entry>Fix Orientation</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Right-handed, Y-up</entry>

                <entry><application>MilkShape</application></entry>

                <entry>MirrorZ <emphasis role="bold">(Automatically set since
                v16fix5)</emphasis></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>

        <para>If you need a transformation matrix, press the
        <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button (c) to open the <guilabel>Matrix
        Editor</guilabel> and press the button name in the table above. Close
        the editor by pressing the <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> button. Back in
        the Model Settings window you can now press the <guibutton>Save
        Default</guibutton> button (d). The transformation matrix you chose
        will then be applied to every new model you add, so you won't have to
        repeat this step.</para>

        <para>The next step is to assign the model texture to your group.
        Usually you should have only one for your first object. If you used
        <application>Biturn</application> to convert your model there will be
        an additional group called <quote>root</quote> (e), just ignore
        it.</para>

        <para><indexterm>
            <primary>Mesh Settings</primary>
          </indexterm><indexterm>
            <primary>Group Settings</primary>
          </indexterm><mousebutton>Click</mousebutton> in the
        <guilabel>Texture</guilabel> column of the group (f) you want to
        assign a texture to (It's name currently should be bright red).</para>

        <para>Select the model texture from the drop-down list. If your object
        has more than one group that should get the same settings, <keycombo>
            <keycap function="control">Ctrl</keycap>

            <mousebutton>Click</mousebutton>
          </keycombo> on the name of the group you want to copy the settings
        from and confirm that you want to copy the settings.</para>

        <para>We are now finished setting up the model, so close the
        <guilabel>Model Settings</guilabel> window by pressing
        <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> (g).</para>
      </section>

      <section id="sect223">
        <title>Set up Levels of Detail (LODs)</title>

        <para>Fortunately for your first object this step is very easy, just
        press the <guibutton>A</guibutton> button in the
        <guilabel>LOD</guilabel> list (6). This will add three default levels
        of detail that use the model you just added.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="sect224">
        <title>Save and Create</title>

        <para>Now everything is set up. First, press the <guiicon>Save
        As</guiicon> button (2) and save the settings for your object to a
        <filename>SCN</filename> file. Now press the
        <guibutton>Create</guibutton> button (7) which should now be enabled
        and say <guibutton>Create Scenery OVL</guibutton> if you did
        everything correctly.</para>

        <para>Select the filename you want to save the
        <filename>OVL</filename> to, do not enter any file extension and keep
        the prefix in the name. You also may only use ASCII characters for it.
        As already mentioned, if you later decide that you want to rename the
        <filename>OVL</filename> file you need to repeat this step, just
        renaming it in the Windows Explorer will <emphasis>not</emphasis>
        work. After a short while you should get a message that the
        <filename>OVL</filename> was created successfully. If not, you didn't
        follow the instructions above (or did something unexpected).</para>

        <para>After successfully creating the <filename>OVL</filename>, press
        the <guiicon>Save</guiicon> button (1) to save your
        <filename>SCN</filename> file again (this will store the path of the
        <filename>OVL</filename> file you just created so you don't have to
        enter it again when you need to recreate it).</para>

        <para>You're now finished creating your first scenery ovl. Press the
        <guiicon>Exit</guiicon> button (3) to go back to the main
        window.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="sect23">
      <title>Create the theme</title>

      <para>Back in the main window we'll now add an icon texture, icon
      references, text strings and the scenery item.</para>

      <section id="sect231">
        <title>Add the icon texture</title>

        <para>Press the <guibutton>Icon Textures</guibutton> button (6) to get
        to the <guilabel>Icon Texture Management</guilabel> window:</para>

        <figure>
          <title>RCT3 Custom Scenery Importer, Management Window</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="manager.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <note>
          <para>As essentially all management windows look the same, no more
          screen shots will be shown.</para>
        </note>

        <para><indexterm>
            <primary>Icon Texture</primary>

            <secondary>Adding</secondary>
          </indexterm><indexterm>
            <primary>Icon Texture, Settings</primary>
          </indexterm>Now press the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button to get
        to the <guilabel>Icon Texture</guilabel> window:</para>

        <figure>
          <title>RCT3 Custom Scenery Importer, Icon Texture Window</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="icontexture.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Press the <guibutton>Load Texture</guibutton> button (b) and
        select your icon texture. As with the model texture, the name (a) will
        be filled in automatically, but you can change it if you want. Press
        <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> (c) when finished and close the management
        window.</para>

        <note>
          <para>As the management window implies you are not restricted to
          only one icon texture, so if you want to create a really large set
          you can add more later.</para>
        </note>
      </section>

      <section id="sect232">
        <title>Add icon references</title>

        <para>Back in the main window press the <guibutton>Icon
        References</guibutton> button (9) to get to the <guilabel>Icon
        Reference Manager</guilabel>. Icon references are needed to tell RCT3
        where on the icon texture the individual icons are placed. We will go
        the easy way, so just press the <guibutton>Auto</guibutton> button,
        leave your icon texture selected in the window that pops up and press
        <guibutton>Ok</guibutton>. This will add references for all icons as
        described above (<xref linkend="sect13" />). Now close the management
        window.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="sect233">
        <title>Add text strings</title>

        <para><indexterm>
            <primary>Text Strings</primary>

            <secondary>Settings</secondary>
          </indexterm>Text strings represent the menu text entries the user
        will see in the game. Open the <guilabel>Text String
        Manager</guilabel> window (8) and press the <guibutton>Add</guibutton>
        button:</para>

        <figure>
          <title>RCT3 Custom Scenery Importer, Text String Window</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="text.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The only thing you need to enter is the text you want to present
        to the user (b). You can also enter a name (a), but if you leave that
        box empty the text will be copied over when you close the window. Now
        enter a group (sub menu) name for your theme, probably the theme name
        and your screen name in some combination. A good idea is either to put
        your name in front (<quote>xyz's abc set</quote>) or last (<quote>abc
        set (xyz)</quote>). Personally I prefer the latter as I tend to
        remember the set name but not who exactly made it.</para>

        <note>
          <para>You can also make scenery items without a group, but this is
          not recommended. They will appear in the big list with all the
          original game items and most likely be missed by the users. Also
          this list is already too big with both extensions installed, so
          please don't make it longer than necessary.</para>
        </note>

        <para>After entering the menu text for the group, close the window by
        pressing <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> (c).</para>

        <para>Back in the manager add another text string for your scenery
        object. The process is the same. When you're finished, close the
        <guilabel>Text String Manager</guilabel> window.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="sect234">
        <title>Add your scenery item</title>

        <para><indexterm>
            <primary>Scenery Item</primary>

            <secondary>Settings</secondary>
          </indexterm>Open the <guilabel>Scenery Item Manager</guilabel>
        window by pressing the respective button (5). After pressing
        <guibutton>Add</guibutton> you get the <guilabel>Scenery Item
        Settings</guilabel> window:</para>

        <figure>
          <title>RCT3 Custom Scenery Importer, Scenery Item Settings
          Window</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="scenery.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>First, press the <guibutton>Select OVL</guibutton> button (a)
        and select the <filename>OVL</filename> you created above (<xref
        linkend="sect22" />). Next enter a location (b). This is the
        subdirectory of your installed theme the <filename>OVL</filename> will
        be placed in. If you can't think of something better, use
        <userinput>misc</userinput>. When you add more items to your set
        later, you can use the drop-down list to select locations you used
        before. As this translates directly into a directory, only ASCII
        characters are allowed.</para>

        <para>If you don't want to use a group you have to disable it using
        the check box (c), but as mentioned above this is not recommended.
        Otherwise select an <guilabel>Icon</guilabel> reference (d) and
        <guilabel>Name String</guilabel> (e) for the
        <guilabel>Group</guilabel>.</para>

        <para>You always have to select an <guilabel>Icon</guilabel> and
        <guilabel>Name String</guilabel> for your <guilabel>Scenery</guilabel>
        item in (f) and (g).</para>

        <para>Next set how much the item will <guilabel>Cost</guilabel> and
        the <guilabel>Refund</guilabel> (j). Actually the latter is a
        misnomer, it is the cost of removing the item, so if you want a real
        refund, enter a negative value. The values you enter here are measured
        in the smallest unit of the users configured currency (e.g. cents for
        Dollars or Euros).</para>

        <para>The <guilabel>Scenery Type</guilabel> (k) selects in which menu
        and category the item will appear. For your first item, select
        <guilabel>Small Scenery</guilabel>. Leave the <guilabel>Support
        Type</guilabel> (l) at <guilabel>None</guilabel> and set
        <guilabel>Extra Parameters</guilabel> (m) to <guilabel>None</guilabel>
        as well.</para>

        <para>All <guilabel>Position</guilabel> parameters (n) should be set
        to <userinput>0</userinput> (zero), the <guilabel>Size in
        squares</guilabel> (p) both to <userinput>1</userinput>. The
        <guilabel>Size</guilabel> (o) should be set to the size of your model
        in modeller units. You have to keep in mind in this case that x/y/z
        here refer to the game's coordinate system. This doesn't matter if you
        didn't need a model transformation matrix or use
        <application>MilkShape</application>. If you had to use the
        <guilabel>Fix Orientation</guilabel> matrix you need to shift the
        values <quote>one up</quote>, so the size in the x direction in your
        modeller goes into <guilabel>Z</guilabel>, y into
        <guilabel>X</guilabel> and z into <guilabel>Y</guilabel>.</para>

        <para>The <guilabel>Placement Flag</guilabel> (q) selects how the game
        will position the object in relation to where the user clicks. For
        your first object, select <guilabel>Full Tile</guilabel>. If you want
        to know more about this setting and how you need to position your
        model correctly for them, see <ulink
        url="http://belgabor.vodhin.net/facts">Belgabor's facts &amp; figures
        page</ulink>.</para>

        <para>We don't need to go into detail for the
        <guilabel>Unknowns</guilabel> (r), not much is known about them
        anyways. Set <guilabel>Unknown1</guilabel> and
        <guilabel>Unknown2</guilabel> to <guilabel>0</guilabel> and enter
        <userinput>0</userinput> (zero) for all others. Leave the flags
        alone.</para>

        <note>
          <para>You can use the <guibutton>Save SID as</guibutton> button (i)
          to save the <guilabel>Scenery Options</guilabel> (with the exception
          of Cost, Refund and Supports Type), <guilabel>Unknowns</guilabel>
          and <guilabel>Flags</guilabel> to a file for later reference (e.g.
          when you want to create several items with the same settings). You
          can open these files with the <guibutton>Open SID</guibutton> button
          (h). There is also a library of sid files dumped form game objects
          on <ulink url="http://www.sebar.com/jonwil">jonwil's
          page</ulink>.</para>
        </note>

        <para>You're finished here, so press <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> (s) to
        close the window. Also close the <guilabel>Scenery Item
        Management</guilabel> window.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="sect24">
      <title>Save and install the theme</title>

      <para>Now we nearly made it. Choose <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>Save Theme File</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> from the menu of the main window to save your theme
      file. Now press the <guibutton>Install</guibutton> button (4) to install
      it. It will be saved to <filename class="directory">&lt;RCT3
      Installation Directory&gt;\Style\Themed</filename> into a subdirectory
      called <filename class="directory">PrefixThemename</filename>. If you
      don't have RCT3 installed, you will be able to select a directory to
      install to instead of <filename class="directory">&lt;RCT3 Installation
      Directory&gt;\Style\Themed</filename>.</para>

      <para>Now start RCT3 and test if everything went well.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Congratulations, you now have imported your
      first RCT3 custom scenery object =)</emphasis></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Credits</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Atari® and Roller Coaster Tycoon 3® are trademarks of Atari Inc.
        All Rights Reserved.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The docbook css used for the html version of this document is
        based upon the one created by <ulink
        url="http://www.karakas-online.de">Chris Karakas</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>This CSS stylesheet uses <ulink
        url="http://www.matterform.com/qbullets/index.php">QBullets</ulink> in
        links. Thanks to Matterform Media for providing QBullets for free. If
        you plan to use them on your website, please observe the <ulink
        url="http://www.matterform.com/qbullets/usage.html">QBullets usage
        terms</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para role="matterform"><ulink
    url="http://www.matterform.com/"><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="/images/qb_credit.gif" scale="100" scalefit="0" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></ulink></para>

    <para><ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/"><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="http://sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=181524&amp;type=4" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="pdf">
          <imagedata fileref="/images/sflogo.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="chm">
          <imagedata fileref="/images/sflogo.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></ulink></para>
  </section>
</article>